In the last few videos, we talked
在之前的视频中 我们讨论了
about how to do forward-propagation
如何使用前向传播
and back-propagation in a
和反向传播
neural network in order to compute derivatives.
计算神经网络中的导数
But back prop as an algorithm
但反向传播作为一个
has a lot of details and,
有很多细节的算法
you know, can be a little
在实现的时候
bit tricky to implement.
会有点复杂
And one unfortunate property is
而且有一个不好的方面是
that there are many
在实现反向传播时
ways to have subtle bugs in back
会遇到很多细小的错误
prop so that if
所以如果你把它和梯度下降法
you run it with gradient descent
或者其他优化算法一起运行时
or some other optimization algorithm, it could actually look like it's working.
可能看起来它运行正常
And, you know, your cost function J
并且 你的代价函数J
of theta may end up
最后可能
decreasing on every iteration
在每次梯度下降法迭代时
of gradient descent, but this
都会减小
could pull through even though
即使在实现反向传播时有一些小错误
there might be some bug in your implementation of back prop.
可能也会检查不出来
So it looks like J of
所以它看起来是
theta is decreasing, but you
J(θ)在减小
might just wind up with
但是可能你最后得到的神经网络
a neural network that
但是可能你最后得到的
has a higher level of error
神经网络误差
than you would with a bug-free
比没有错误的要高
implementation and you might
而且你很可能
just not know that there
就是不知道
was this subtle bug that's giving
你的结果是这些
you this performance.
小错误导致的
So what can we do about this?
那你应该怎么办呢
There's an idea called gradient checking
有一个想法叫梯度检验 (Gradient Checking)
that eliminates almost all of these problems.
可以解决基本所有的问题
So today, every time I
我现在每次实现
implement back propagation or a
神经网络的反向传播
similar gradient descent algorithm on
或者类似的
the neural network or any other
梯度下降算法
reasonably complex model, I
或者其他比较复杂的模型
always implement gradient checking.
我都会使用梯度检验
And if you do this it will
如果你这么做
help you make sure and
它会帮你确定
sort of gain high confidence that
并且能很确信
your implementation of forward prop
你实现的前向传播和反向传播
and back prop or whatever, is 100% correct.
或者其他的什么 是100%正确的
And in what I've seen
我见过很多
this pretty much all the
这样解决那些
problems associated with sort of
实现时容易有
a buggy implementation of the background.
有小错误的问题
And in the previous videos,
在之前的视频中
I sort of ask you to take on
我一般是让你相信
faith that the formulas I
我给出的计算
gave for computing the deltas, and the
δ，d项
D's, and so on, I ask
等等之类的公式
you to take on faith that those
我要求你们相信
actually do compute the gradients
他们计算的就是
of the cost function, but once
代价函数的梯度
you implement numerical gradient checking,
但一旦你们实现数值梯度检验
which is the topic of this video,
也就是这节视频的主题
you'll be able to verify for
你就能够自己验证
yourself that the code you're
你写的代码
writing is indeed computing
确实是在计算
the derivative of the cost
代价函数J的导数
function J.  So here's the idea.
想法是这样的
Consider the following example.
考虑下面这个例子
Suppose I have the function
假如我有一个
J of theta, and I
函数J(θ)
have some value, theta, and
并且我有个值 θ
for this example, I'm going to assume that theta is just a real number.
在这个例子中 我假定θ只是一个实数
And let's say I want to estimate the derivative of this function at this point.
假如说我想估计这个函数在这一点的导数
And so the derivative is, you know, equal
这个导数等于
to the slope of that sort of tangent line.
这条切线的斜率
Here's how I'm going to numerically
下面我要用数值方法
approximate the derivative, or
来计算近似的导数
rather here's a procedure for numerically
这个是用数值方法
approximating the derivative: I'm
计算近似导数的过程
going to compute theta plus epsilon,
我要计算θ+ε
so value a little bit to the right.
这个值在右边一点
And we are going to compute theta minus epsilon.
然后计算θ-ε
And I'm going to look
然后看这两个点
at those two points and connect
用一条直线
them by a straight line.
把它们连起来
And I'm going to connect
我要把这两个点
these two points by a straight
用一条直线连起来
line and I'm going to
然后用这条
use the slope of that
红色线的斜率
little red line as my
来作为我
approximation to the derivative,
导数的近似值
which is the true derivative is
真正的导数是这边这条
the slope of the blue line over there.
蓝色线的斜率
So, you know, it seems like it would be a pretty good approximation.
这看起来是个不错的近似
Mathematically, the slope of this
在数学上 这条红线的斜率等于
red line is this vertical
这个垂直的高度
height, divided by this
除以这个
horizontal width, so this
这个水平的宽度
point on top is J of
所以上面这点
theta plus epsilon. This point
是J(θ+ε)
here is J of theta minus epsilon.
这点是J(Θ-ε)
So this vertical difference is j
垂直方向上的
of theta plus epsilon, minus J
差是J(θ+ε)-J(θ+ε)
of theta, minus epsilon, and
也就是说
this horizontal distance is just 2 epsilon.
水平的距离就是2ε
So, my approximation is going
那么 我的近似是这样的
to be that the derivative,
J(θ)
with respect to theta of J of
对θ的导数
theta--add this value of
近似等于
theta--that that's approximately J
J(θ+ε)-J(θ-ε)
of theta plus epsilon, minus
除以2ε
J of theta, minus epsilon, over 2 epsilon.
近似于J(θ+ε)-J(θ-ε) 除以2ε
Usually, I use a pretty
通常
small value for epsilon and
我给ε取很小的值
set epsilon to be maybe
比如可能取
on the order of 10 to the minus 4.
10的-4次方
There's usually a large range
ε的取值在一个
of different values for epsilon that work just fine.
很大范围内都是可行的
And in fact, if you
实际上
let epsilon become really small
如果你让ε非常小
then, mathematically, this term here
那么 数学上
actually, mathematically, you know,
这里这项实际上就是导数
becomes the derivative, becomes exactly
就变成了函数
the slope of the function at this point.
在这点上准确的斜率
It's just that we don't want
只是我们不想用
to use epsilon that's too, too
非常非常小的ε
small because then you might run into numerical problems.
因为可能会产生数值问题
So, you know, I usually use
所以我通常让ε
epsilon around 10 to the minus 4, say.
差不多等于10^-4
And by the way some of you may
顺便说一下 可能你们有些学习者
have seen it alternative formula for
见过另外这种
estimating the derivative which is this formula.
估计导数的公式
This one on the right is called the one-sided difference.
右边这个叫做单侧拆分
Whereas, the formula on the left that's called a two-sided difference.
左边这个公式叫做双侧差分
The two-sided difference gives
双侧差分给我们了一个
us a slightly more accurate estimate,
稍微精确些的估计
so I usually use that rather
所以我通常用那个
than just this one-sided difference estimate.
而不用这个单侧差分估计
So, concretely, what you implement
具体地说 你在Octave中实现时
in Octave is you implement the following.
要使用下面这个
You implement call to compute, gradApprox
你的程序要调用
which is going to
gradApprox来计算
be approximation to zero relative
这个函数
as just, you know, this formula: J of
会通过这个公式
theta plus epsilon, minus J of theta,
J(θ+ε)-J(θ-ε)
minus epsilon, divided by two times epsilon.
除以2ε
And this will give you a
它会给出这点导数的
numerical estimate of the gradient at that point.
数值估计
And in this example it seems like it's a pretty good estimate.
在这个例子中 它看起来是个很好的估计
Now, on the previous slide,
在之前的幻灯片中
we consider the case of
我们考虑了
when theta was a real number.
θ是一个实数的情况
Now, let's look at the more
现在我们看更普遍的情况
general case of where theta is a vector parameter.
θ是一个向量参数
So let's say theta is an
假如说θ是n维向量
Rn, and it might be unreal
它可能是我们的
version of the parameters of
神经网络参数的
our neural network. So
展开形式
theta is a vector that
所以θ是一个有
has n elements, theta 1
有n个元素的向量
up to theta n. We
θ1到θn
can then use a similar idea
我们可以用类似的想法
to approximate all of the partial derivative terms.
来估计所有的偏导数项
Concretely, the partial derivative
具体地说
of a cost function with respect
代价函数对
to the first parameter theta
第一个参数θ1取偏导数
1, that can be
它可以用J
obtained by taking J and increasing theta 1.
和增大的θ1得到
So you have J of theta 1 plus epsilon, and so on
所以你有J(θ1+ε) 等等
minus J of this theta
减去J(θ1-ε)
1 minus epsilon and divide it by 2 epsilon.
然后除以2ε
The partial derivative respect to
对第二个参数θ2
the second parameter theta 2, is
取偏导数
again this thing, except you're
还是这样
taking J of, here you're
除了你要对
increasing theta 2 by epsilon.
θ2+ε取J
And here you're decreasing theta 2 by epsilon.
这里还有θ2-ε
And so on down to the
这样计算后面的偏导数
derivative with respect to
直到θn
theta n. Would be if you
它的算法是
increase and decrease theta n
对θn增加
by epsilon over there.
和减少ε
So, these equations give
这些公式
you a way to numerically approximate
给出一个计算J
the partial derivative of "J"
对任意参数求偏导数的
with respect to any one of your parameters they derive.
数值近似的方法
Concretely, what you implement is therefore, the following.
具体地说 你要实现的是下面这个
We implement the following in Octave
我们把这个用在Octave里
to numerically compute the derivatives.
来计算数值导数
We say for i equals 1
假如 i
through n where n is
等于 1 到 n
the dimension of our parameter vector theta.
n是我们的参数向量θ的维度
And I usually do this with the unrolled version of the parameters.
我通常用参数的展开形式来计算
So you know theta is just
你知道θ只是我们
a long list of all of my parameters in my neural networks.
神经网络模型的一长列参数
I'm going to set theta plus equals
我让thetaPlus等于theta
theta, then increase theta plus
然后给thetaPlus的第 i 项
the ith element by epsilon.
加上EPSILON
And so this is basically
这就是基本的
theta plus is equal to theta
thetaPlus等于theta
except for theta plus i,
除了thetaPlus(i)
which is now incremented by epsilon.
它会增加EPSILON
So if theta plus
所以如果thetaPlus
is equal to, right, theta
等于θ1 θ2 等等
1, theta 2, and so on and then theta
那么θi
i has epsilon added to
增加了EPSILON
it, and then it go down to
然后一直到θn
theta n. So this is what theta plus is.
这就是thetaPlus的作用
And similarly these two
类似的 这两行
lines set theta minus to
给thetaMinus
something similar except that
类似地赋值
this, instead of theta i
只是θi不是加EPSILON
plus epsilon, this now becomes theta i minus epsilon.
而是减EPSILON
And then finally, you implement
最后 你运行这个
this gradApprox i,
gradApprox(i)
and this will give you
它会给你近似的
your approximation to the partial
J(θ)对θi的
derivative with respect to
偏导数
theta i of J of theta.
我们实现
And the way we use this
神经网络时
in our neural network implementation is
是这样用的
we would implement this, implement this
我们要实现这个
FOR loop to compute, you know, the top partial
用for循环来计算
derivative of the cost
代价函数对
function with respect to every parameter in our network.
每个网络中的参数的偏导数
And we can then take the
然后我们用从
gradient that we got from back prop.
反向传播得到的梯度
So DVec was the derivatives
DVec是我们从反向传播中
we got from back prop.
得到的导数
Right, so back prop, back-propagation was
所以后向传播是一个
a relatively efficient way to
相对比较有效率的
compute the derivatives or the
计算代价函数
partial derivatives of a
对参数的导数
cost function with respect to all of our parameters.
或偏导数的方法
And what I usually do
接下来
is then take my numerically
我通常做的是
computed derivative, that is
计算数值导数
this gradApprox that we
就是gradApprox
just had from up here and
我们刚从上面这里得到的
make sure that that is
来确定它等于
equal or approximately equal
或者近似于
up to, you know, small values
差距很小
of numerical round off that is
非常接近我们
pretty close to the DVec that I got from back prop.
从反向传播得到的DVec
And if these two ways
如果这两种
of computing the derivative give me
计算导数的方法
the same answer or at least give me
给你相同的结果或者非常接近结果
very similar answers, you know, up to a few decimal places.
最多几位小数的差距
Then I'm much more confident that
那么我就非常确信
my implementation of back prop is correct.
我实现的反向传播时正确的
And when I plug these DVec
然后我把这些DVec向量用在
vectors into gradient descent
梯度下降法或者
or some advanced optimization algorithm,
其他高级优化算法里
I can then be much
然后我就可以比较确信
more confident that I'm computing
我计算的导数
the derivatives correctly and therefore,
是正确的
that hopefully my codes will
那么 我的代码
run correctly and do a
应该也可以正确运行
good job optimizing J of theta.
可以很好地优化J(θ)
Finally, I want to put
最后 我想把
everything together and tell you
所有的东西放在一起
how to implement this numerical gradient checking.
然后告诉你怎么实现这个数值梯度检验
Here's what I usually do.
这是我通常做的
First thing I do, is implement
第一件事
back-propagation to compute defects.
是实现反向传播来计算DVec
So, this is a procedure we talked
这个步骤是我们
about in an earlier video to
之前的视频中讲过的
compute DVec which may be our unrolled version of these matrices.
计算DVec 它可能是这些矩阵的展开形式
Then what I do, is implement
然后我要做的是
a numerical gradient checking to compute gradApprox.
用gradApprox实现数值梯度检验
So this is what I described earlier in this video, in the previous slide.
这是我在这节视频前面部分讲的 在之前的幻灯片里
Then you should make sure that DVec and gradApprox
然后你要确定DVec和gradApprox给出接近的结果
gives similar values, you know, let's say up to a few decimal places.
可能最多差几位小数
And finally, and this
最后
the important step, the more
这是最重要的一步
you start to use your code
在使用你的代码去学习
for learning, for seriously training
训练你的网络之前
your network, it is important to turn off gradient checking.
重要的是要关掉梯度检验
And to no longer compute
不再使用
this gradApprox thing using
这节视频前面讲的
the numerical derivative formulas that
这个数值导数公式
we talked about earlier in this
来计算
video.
gradApprox
And the reason for that is the
这样做的原因是
numeric code gradient checking code,
我们之前讲的这个
the stuff we talked about in
数值梯度检验代码
this video, that's a very
是一个计算量
computationally expensive, that's a
非常大的程序
very slow way to try to approximate the derivative.
它是一个非常慢的计算近似导数的方法
Whereas in contrast, the back-propagation
而相对地
algorithm that we talked about
我们之前讲的
earlier, that is the
反向传播算法
thing that we talked about earlier
也就是那个
for computing, you know, D1, D2,
DVec的D(1) D(2) D(3)的算法
D3, or for DVec. Back prop is
反向传播是一个在计算导数上
a much more computationally efficient way of computing the derivatives.
效率更高的方法
So once you've verified that
所以当你确认了
your implementation of back-propagation is
你的反向传播算法是正确的
correct, you should turn
你应该关掉梯度检验
off gradient checking, and just stop using that.
就是不使用它
So just to reiterate, you
再重申一下
should be sure to disable your
在为了训练分类器
gradient checking code before running
运行你的算法
your algorithm for many
做很多次梯度下降
iterations of gradient descent, or
或高级优化算法的迭代之前
for many iterations of the
要确定你
advanced optimization algorithms in
不再使用
order to train your classifier.
梯度检验的程序
Concretely, if you were
具体来说
to run numerical gradient checking
如果你在每次的梯度下降法迭代时
on every single integration of gradient
都运行数值梯度检验
descent, or if you were in the
或者你用在
inner loop of your cost function,
代价函数的内循环里
then your code will be very slow.
你的程序会变得非常慢
Because the numerical gradient checking
因为数值梯度检验程序
code is much slower than
比反向传播算法
the back-propagation algorithm, than
要慢很多
a back-propagation method where you
反向传播算法
remember we were computing delta
就是我们计算
4, delta 3, delta 2, and so on.
δ(4) δ(3) δ(2) 等等的
That was the back-propagation algorithm.
那就是反向传播算法
That is a much faster way to compute derivatives than gradient checking.
那是一个比梯度检验更快的计算导数的方法
So when you're ready, once
所以当你准备好了
you verify the implementation of back-propagation
一旦你验证了
is correct, make sure you
反向传播的实现是正确的
turn off, or you disable
要确定你在训练算法时把它关闭了
your gradient checking code while
或者说不再使用梯度检验程序
you train your algorithm, or else your code could run very slowly.
否则你的程序会运行得非常慢
So that's how you take gradients numerically.
所以如果你计算用数值方法计算导数
And that's how you can verify that
那是你用来确定反向传播实现
your implementation of back-propagation is correct.
是否正确的的方法
Whenever I implement back-propagation or
当我实现反向传播
similar gradient descent algorithm for
或者类似的复杂模型的梯度下降算法
a complicated model, I always use gradient checking.
我经常使用梯度检验
This really helps me make sure that my code is correct.
这的确能帮我确定我的代码是正确的